Guide to the Frederic B.M. Hollyday papers, 1818-1982, bulk 1860s-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frederic B.M. Hollyday papers 1818-1982, bulk 1860s-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hollyday, Frederic B.M., 1928-
2.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 298 Items
Frederic Hollyday was a professor of German history in the Department of History at Duke University, Durham, North Carolina. Collection consists chiefly of letters of the Kennedy, Mumford, Hewlett, and Mann families, mainly from Michigan, containing some references to state political matters and the Civil War; letters and papers of Willoughby O'Donoughue, surgeon of the 1st Michigan Regiment, Engineers and Mechanics, with enlistment and discharge papers, mustering-out lists, and papers concerning the Grand Army of the Republic; and papers of Frederick Blackmar Mumford, dean of the University of Missouri College of Agriculture, including family letters, clippings, pictures, legal papers, diplomas and special awards, a diary, 1945, and a scrapbook tracing Mumford's career, 1917-1938. In addition, the collection includes correspondence pertaining to the controversy over the negotiations about establishing the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library at Duke; genealogy and family history of the Hollyday and Kennedy families; photographs; a scrapbook of correspondence, genealogical information, a diary in typescript, and legal papers, of the Mumford, Kennedy, Camburn, Strong and Hoskins families; Frederick Blackmar Mumford's (Hollyday's grandfather) travel diary describing Europe in 1900; and Prussian legal documents of the Dallmar family, 1850-1885.
RL.00562
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Frederic B.M. Hollyday papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1969, 1981, 1982, and 1987.
Collection Overview
Collection consists chiefly of three main groups of papers. The first comprises letters of the Kennedy, Mumford, Hewlett, and Mann families, mainly from Michigan, containing some references to state political matters and the Civil War. The second contains correspondence and papers of Willoughby O'Donoughue, surgeon of the 1st Michigan Regiment, Engineers and Mechanics, contain enlistment and discharge papers, mustering-out lists, and papers concerning the Grand Army of the Republic. The third group comprises the papers of Frederick Blackmar Mumford, dean of the University of Missouri College of Agriculture, and includes family letters, clippings, pictures, legal papers, diplomas and special awards, a diary, 1945, and a scrapbook tracing Mumford's career, 1917-1938.
In addition, the collection includes correspondence pertaining to the controversy over the negotiations about establishing the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library at Duke as well as an agenda for the meetings of the Academic Council on the same issue. Correspondents include: Edwin H. Cady; Jay Luvaas, Professor of History at Allegheny College and Ph.D. graduate at Duke; Roger Marshall, Special Assistant to President Sanford; Terry Sanford, President of Duke University; and Richard L. Watson, Jr., Acting Chairman of the History Department.
Other papers in the collection include genealogy and family history of the Hollyday and Kennedy families; photographs; a scrapbook of correspondence, genealogy, diary in typescript, legal papers and other documents of the Mumford, Kennedy, Camburn, Strong and Hoskins families; Frederick Blackmar Mumford's (Hollyday's grandfather) travel diary describing Europe in 1900; and Prussian legal documents of the Dallmar family, 1850-1885.
Subject Headings
Mumford, Frederic Blackmar; O'Donoughue, Willoughby; Camburn family; Dallmar family; Hewlett family; Kennedy family; Hoskins family; Mann family; Mumford family; Strong family; Grand Army of the Republic; United States. Army. Michigan Engineers and Mechanics, 1st Regiment (1861-1865); United States. Army -- Surgeons; University of Missouri -- Faculty; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Agricultural education -- United States; College teachers -- Correspondence; Europe -- Description and travel; Michigan -- Genealogy; Michigan -- Politics and government; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories; Diaries; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Related Material
Frederic B.M. Hollyday papers (University Archives collection)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Frederic B.M. Hollyday papers, 1818-1982, bulk 1860s-1946, 4 boxes
  - Papers, 1842-1969 (Box 1)
  - O'Donoughue division papers, 1861-1915 (Box 1)
  - Mumford division papers, 1882-1946 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1818-1982 (Box 2)
  - O'Donoughue division memorabilia (Box 3)
  - Mumford division volumes (Box 3)
  - Addition, 1987 (Box 4)
    Contains various correspondence, photographs, and other memorabilia concerning the Kennedy, Mumford, and Dallmar families as well as one records volume.
- Oversize Materials, 1883-1945, 17 items
  - Description of Certificate of Seventh Degree. Order of the Patrons of Husbandry (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Diploma, Hanover Grammar School, 1883 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Diploma, Hanover Union School, 1885 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, Red Cross Society of Brooklyn New York (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, 20th Annual Session of the State Grange of Michigan (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Diploma, Brooklyn Normal School for Physical Education, 1891 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - United States of America Universal Exposition Saint Louis Commemorative Diploma (member, jury of awards on cattle) (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Diploma, State Agricultural College, Michigan, 1891 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Columbian Exposition, Diploma of Honorable Mention, 1894 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - [Certificate of Safe conduct], 1900 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1900 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, Degree of Ceres, Order of the Patrons of Husbandry, 1912 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, United States Council of National defense, 1919 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Diploma, Michigan State College of Agriculture and Applied Science, 1927 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, The Curators of the University of Missouri, 1939 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Certificate, State of Maryland Public Schools, 1941 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)
  - Diploma, Maryland High School Diploma, 1945 (Box Ovsz. Box 36)